Okay.
This is it. This is then the second
lecture in linear algebra.
And
I've put below
my main topics for today.
That I I put right there a system of
equations. That's going to be our
example to work with. But let me What
are we going to do with it?
We're going to solve it.
And the method of solution will not be
determinants.
Determinants are something that will
come later. The method we'll use is
called elimination.
And
it's the way every
software package solves equations.
And
so and and elimination
uh well, if it succeeds, it gets the
answer.
And normally it does succeed. If the
matrix A that's coming into that system
is a good matrix and I think this one
is,
then elimination will work. We'll get
the answer in an efficient way.
But why don't we, as long as we're sort
of seeing how elimination works, it's
always good to ask how could it fail?
So at the same time we'll see we'll see
how elimination decides whether the
matrix is a good one or has
has problems.
Then to complete the answer, there's a
obvious step of back substitution. In
fact,
the idea of elimination is
you would have thought of it.
Right? Uh
I mean, Gauss thought of it before we
did, but only because he was
born earlier. It's a natural idea.
Uh
uh
and died earlier, too. Okay, so uh
but then
and you've seen the idea.
But now
the part that I want to show you is
elimination expressed in matrix language
cuz the whole course
all the key ideas get expressed as
matrix operations,
not as words.
And
one of the operations, of course, that
we'll meet is how do we multiply
matrices and why. Okay, so there's a
system of equations.
Three equations in three unknowns.
And there's the matrix, the 3 by 3
matrix that that So, this is the system
uh
Ax = b, you could say. This is This is
our system to solve. Ax = and the
right-hand side is that vector 2 12 2.
Okay.
Now,
uh when I describe elimination,
it gets to be a pain to keep writing the
equal signs and the pluses and so on.
It's the It's that matrix that's that
that totally matters.
Everything is in that matrix.
But behind it is those equations. So,
what does elimination do?
What's the first step of elimination?
We
we we accept the first equation, it's
okay.
I'm going to multiply that equation by
the right number, the right multiplier,
and I'm going to subtract it
from the second equation.
With what purpose? So, what what
what that will decide what the
multiplier should be. Our purpose is to
knock out
the X
part of equation two.
So, our purpose is to reduce, to
eliminate X.
So, what do I multiply
And again, I'll do it with this matrix
cuz I can do it short.
What what's the multiplier here? What do
I multiply equation one and subtract?
Notice I'm saying that word subtract. I
I'd like to stick to that convention.
I'll do a subtraction. So, what First of
all,
this is the key number, right? That I
I'm starting with.
And that's called the pivot.
I'll put a box around it and and write
its name down. That's the first pivot.
The first pivot.
Okay, so I'm going to use
that's sort of like the key number in
that equation. And now, what's the
multiplier? So, I'm going to I'm going
to
Uh my first row won't change.
But I mean that's the pivot row. But I'm
going to use it.
And now finally, let me ask what the
multiplier is. Yes.
Three. Three times that first equation
will knock out that three.
Okay. So, what will it leave? So, the
multiplier is three. Three times that
will leave will make that zero. That was
our purpose. Three twos away from the
eight will leave a two. And three ones
away from one will leave a minus two.
And this guy didn't change.
Okay.
Now, the next step. So, that step of
This is forward elimination and that
step's completed. Oh, well, you could
say, "Wait a minute. What about the
right-hand side?"
Shall I carry The right-hand side is
like
gets carried along. I actually MATLAB
finishes up with the left side before
and then just goes back to do the right
side. Maybe I
I'll be MATLAB for for a moment and do
that. Okay, so I just like I'm leaving a
column room for a column of B, the
right-hand side, but I will I'll fill it
in later. Okay.
Now, the next step of elimination is
what? Well, strictly speaking,
I should I cleaned up this was the
This position that I cleaned up was like
the 2 1 position,
row two, column one. So, I got a zero in
the 2 1 position. I'll I'll use 2 1 as
the index of that step. The next step
should be to finish the column and
get a zero in that position.
So, the next step is really the 3 1
step, row three, column one. But, of
course, I already have
zero. Okay. So, so the multiplier is
zero. I take zero of this equation away
from this one, and uh
I'm all set. So, I won't repeat that,
but there was a step there which
uh
MATLAB would have to look. It would look
at this number
and
uh do that step unless you told it in
advance that it was zero. Okay. Now, uh
now what? Now, we can see the second
pivot,
which is what?
The second pivot See, we've eliminated
X is now gone from this equation, right?
We're We're down to two equations
in Y and Z.
And so, now I just do it again. Like,
everything's recursive at this This is a
such a basic algorithm, and it's and
you've seen it. But, carry me through
one last step.
What What's the So, this is still the
first pivot.
Now, the second pivot is this guy who's
who's appeared there. And what's the
multiplier the appropriate multiplier
now?
I And what And what's my purpose? Is to
clean up the Is to wipe out the 3 2
position, right? This was the This was
the two one step. And now I'm going to
take the
three two step.
So, this all stays the same.
1 2 1
0 2 -1
and the the pivot are there. Now I'm
using this pivot. So, what's the
multiplier?
Two.
Two times this equation, this row, gets
subtracted from this row and makes that
a zero. So, it's zero zero and what's
Is it a five?
Yeah, I guess it's a five. Is that
right?
Cuz I have a one there and I'm
subtracting
twice of the twice this, so I it think
it it's a five there. There's the third
pivot. So, let me put a box around all
three pivots.
Is there a
I think that's Oh, did I just invent a
negative one?
I I I'm sorry that the tape can't
the
correct that as easily as I can. Okay,
is that Thank you very much.
Uh
You get an A in the course now. Is that
Is that Is that correct?
Is it correct now?
Okay.
So, the three pivots are there.
Uh
I I know right away a lot about this
matrix. The this this elimination step
from A this this matrix I'm going to
call U.
U for upper triangular. So, the whole
purpose of elimination was to get from A
to U.
And literally that's the most common
calculation in scientific computing.
And any And people think of how could I
do that faster because it's a major
major
thing.
But we're doing it the straightforward
way.
We found three pivots. And by the way, I
didn't say this.
Pivots can't be zero.
I don't accept zero as a pivot. And I
didn't get zero.
So this this matrix is great. It gave me
three pivots.
I didn't have to do anything special. I
just followed the rules and
uh
and uh the pivots are 1, 2, and 5.
By the way, just cuz I always anticipate
stuff from a later day, if I wanted to
know the determinant of the the
determinant of this matrix, which I
never do want to know, uh but I would
just multiply the pivots. The
determinant is 10. So even things like
the determinant are are uh
are here.
Okay.
Now Oh, let me talk about failure for a
moment and then
and then uh
come back to success. Uh How could this
have failed?
How could
um
Well, how could By fail, I mean fail to
come up with three pivots.
What How Tell me I mean there are a
couple of points.
I would have already been in trouble if
this first very first number here was
zero. If it was a zero there,
suppose that had been a zero. There were
no x's in that equation first equation.
It
Does that mean I can't solve the
problem? Does that mean I quit?
No.
What do I do?
I ex- switch rows. I exchange rows. So
in case of a zero, I I will not say zero
pivot.
I will never be heard to utter those
words, zero pivot. But, if there's a
zero in the pivot position, maybe I can
say that, I would try to exchange for a
lower equation and get a non get a
proper pivot up there. Okay. Now, for
example,
this second pivot came out two. Could it
have come out zero? What Actually, if I
change that eight a little bit,
I would have got again
a a little trouble. What What should I
change that eight to so that I get some
so that I run into trouble?
A six. If that had been a six,
then this would have been
zero and I couldn't have used that as
the pivot, but I could have exchanged
again.
In this case,
in this case, because what When can I
When can I get out of trouble?
I can get out of trouble if there's a
non-zero below this this troublesome
zero. And there is here.
So, I would be okay in this case. If
this was a six, I would survive by a row
exchange.
Now,
of course,
it might have happened that I couldn't
do the row that that there was zeros
below it, but here there wasn't. Now, I
could also have got in trouble if this
number one was a little different.
See, that one became a five, I guess, by
the end.
So, do you do you Can you see what
number there would have got me trouble
that I really couldn't get out of?
Trouble that I couldn't get out of would
mean if the pivot is
All right. If the if zero is in the
pivot position and I can't I've got no
place to exchange. So, there there there
must be some number
which if I had had here, it would have
meant failure.
Negative four, good.
If it was a negative four here, if it
happened to be a negative four, can I
can I I'll temporarily put it up here.
If If this had been a negative
four Z, then I would have gone through
the same steps. This would have been a
minus four. It still would have been a
minus four. But at the last minute it
would have become zero.
And there wouldn't have been a third
pivot. The matrix would have not been
invertible.
Of course, the inverse of a matrix is
coming next week, but uh
you've heard these words before. So,
that that's how we we we identify
failure.
There's temporary failure when we can do
a row exchange and and get out of it. Or
there's complete failure when we get a
zero and
and there's nothing below that we can
use. Okay.
Let's stay with uh back to success now.
In fact, I guess the next topic is back
substitution.
So, what's back substitution? Well, that
Now, I better bring the right hand side
in.
So, what would MATLAB do?
And what should we do? Let's Let's Let
me bring in the right hand side as an
extra column.
So, there comes B. So, it's 2 12 2.
This is I I would call this the
augmented matrix. Augment means you've
tacked something on. I've tacked on this
extra column.
Because when I'm working with equations,
I do the same thing to both sides.
So, at this step, I I
two of the first equation away from the
second equation so that this
augmented shall I I even brought some
colored chalk, but I don't know
if it shows up. So, this is like the
augmented
No, damn.
Circle the wrong thing. Okay, here's the
Here is B.
Okay, that's the extra column. Okay, so
what happened
to that extra column, the right-hand
side of the equations when I did the
first step? So, with that was three of
this away from this, so it took the two
stayed the same,
but three twos got taken away from 12
leaving six, and that two stayed the
same. So, this is the
how it's looking halfway along, and then
let me just carry to the end. The two
and the six stay the same, but
what do I have here?
Oh, gosh.
Uh help me out now. What So, now I'm I'm
This is This is still like forward
elimination.
I I got to this point, which I think is
right.
And now, what did I do with this step? I
multiplied that pivot by two or that
whole equation by two and subtracted
from that. So, I think I take two sixes,
which is 12 away from the two. Do you
think minus 10
is my final right-hand side?
The right-hand side that goes with U,
and let me call that once and forever
the vector C.
So, C is what happens to B,
and U is what happens to A.
Okay, there you've seen elimination
clean. Okay.
Oh, what's back substitution?
So, So, what are my final equations
then? Can I Can I copy these equations?
Uh x + 2y + z = 2 is still there. And 2y
- 2z = 6 is there. And 5z is -10.
Okay.
That Those are the equations that are
that these numbers are telling me about.
That Those are the equations Ux = c.
Okay, how do I solve them?
What do What one do I solve for first?
z I see immediately that the correct
value of z is
-2.
And what do I do next?
I go back upwards. I now know z here.
So,
uh if z is -2, that's four there. Is
that right?
And so, 2y + the four is six. Maybe y is
one.
Going This is This is back substitution.
We're doing it on the fly cuz it's so
easy. And then x
is
So, x 2y's is 2 - 2. Maybe x is 2.
So, you see what back substitution is.
It's the
simple step solving the equations in
reverse order because the system is
triangular. Okay.
Good.
So, that's elimination and back
substitution. And I kept the right-hand
side along.
Okay, now what do I What So, that
That like is
first
piece of the lecture.
What's the second piece?
Matrices are going to get in. So, So, I
first I wrote stuff with X's, Y's, and
Z's in there. Then I really
got the right shorthand just writing the
matrix entries.
And now I want to write the operations
that I did
in matrices, right? I've carried the
matrices along, but I haven't said
the
operation
that those those elimination steps I I
now want to express as matrices. Okay,
here they come.
So, now this is elimination matrices.
Okay. Let me take that Let me take that
first step, which which took me from 1 2
1 3 8 1
0 4 1.
I I want to operate on that. I'm I'm
want to do uh elimination on that.
Okay.
Okay. Now, actually I'm I'm remembering
a point I want to I want to
single out as as
as
uh specially important. Let me Let me
move the board up
for that.
Cuz
when we do matrix operations, we got to
like be able to see the big picture.
Okay, last time I spoke about
the big picture of when I multiply a
matrix by a right-hand side. If I have
some matrix there, and I multiply it by
3 4 5, let's say.
So, here's a matrix.
What did I say? Well, I guess I only
said it on the videotape, but
do you remember
how I look at that matrix
multiplication,
the result of multiplying a matrix by
some vector
is a combination of the
columns
of the matrix. It's three times the
first column.
It's three times column one
plus four times column two
plus five times column three.
Okay. I'm going to come back to that
multiple times. What I wanted to do now
was to emphasize the
parallel thing with rows.
Why? Because all our operations here for
this like this two weeks of the course
are row operations. So, I have to
So, if this isn't
what I need for row operations, let me
let me
let me do a row operation. Suppose I
have my matrix
again
and suppose I multiply on the left by
some, let's say 1 2 7.
Again, I'm just like saying what the
result is.
And then we'll
say how matrix multiplication works and
we'll see that it's true.
Okay.
But
maybe already I'm making uh uh uh
I'm sort of bringing up the central idea
of linear algebra is
how these matrices work by rows as well
as by columns. Okay, how does it work by
rows? What what
So, this is a
that that's a row vector.
It's a It's I could say that's a 1 by 3
matrix.
A row vector multiplying a 3 by 3
What
What's the output?
What's the product of a row times a
matrix?
And okay, it's a row.
A row A column
I Sorry, a matrix times a column is a
column. So, matrix
times a Yeah, matrix
times a column
is a column.
And we know what column it is. Over
here, I'm doing a row times a matrix,
and what And what is the What's the
answer? It's one of that first row. So,
it's 1 * 1 * row 1
plus
2 * row 2
plus 7 * row 3.
When as we do matrix multiplication,
keep your eye on
what it's doing with whole vectors.
And what it's doing what what it's doing
in this case is it's combining the rows.
We have a combination a linear
combination of the rows. Okay, I want to
use that.
Okay. Now, So, my question is, what's
the matrix that does this first step?
That takes
subtracts three of equation one from
equation two. That's what I want to do.
So, this is going to be a a matrix
that's going to subtract
3 * * row 1
from row two.
And leaves the other rows the same. Just
just I mean the answer is going to be
that.
So, whatever matrix this is
and you're going to like tell me what
matrix will do it. It's the matrix that
leaves the first row unchanged, leaves
the last row unchanged, but takes three
of these away from this. So, it puts a
zero there, a two there, and a minus
two.
Good.
What matrix will do it?
It's these.
It should be a pretty simple matrix
cuz we're doing a very simple step.
We're just doing this step that changes
row two. So, actually row one is not
changing. So,
tell me how the matrix should begin.
One
So, the first row of the matrix will be
one
zero zero.
Because that's just the right thing.
That takes one of that row and none of
the other rows, and that's what we want.
What's the last row of the matrix?
Zero zero one.
Cuz that takes
one of the third row and none of the
other rows. That's great. Okay.
Now, suppose I didn't want to do
anything at all.
Suppose my row Well, I guess maybe I had
a a case here when I already had a zero
and didn't have to do anything. What
matrix does nothing?
Like just leaves you where you were.
If I put in
if I put in zero one zero, that would be
that would be
That's the matrix. What's the name of
that matrix?
The identity matrix, right.
So it does absolutely nothing. It just
multiplies everything and leaves it
where it is. It's like a one, like the
number one for matrices. But that that's
not what we want cuz we want to change
this
row two.
Uh so, what's the correct
What should I put in here now to come
out to do to do it right?
I want to get What do I want What am I
I'm after? I want to sub tract my I I I
want
three of row one to get subtracted off.
So what's that row What's the right
matrix to finish that matrix for me?
But -3 goes here.
And what goes here? That one. And what
goes here? The zero.
That's the good matrix. That's the
matrix that takes
-3 of row one plus the row two and gives
the new row two. Should we just like
check
uh some
particular entry? How How do I check a
particular entry of a matrix in in
matrix multiplication? Like suppose I
wanted to check the entry here that's in
row two, column three.
So where does the entry in row two,
column three come from?
I would look at row two of this guy
and column
three of this one
to get that number. That number comes
from the second row and the third column
and I just take this
dot product. -3 I'm multiplying. -3 + 1
and 0 gives the -2.
Yeah, it it works.
So we got various ways to multiply
matrices now.
We're We're sort of like informally
we've got by columns, we've got Well, we
will have by columns, by rows, by each
entry at a time, but
it's good to see that matrix
multiplication when one of the matrices
is so simple. So, this guy
is our elementary matrix. Let's Let's
call it E for elementary or elimination.
And let me put the indexes 2 1
because it's the matrix that we needed
to fix the 2 1 position. It's the It's
the matrix that we needed to get this
2 1 position to be zero.
Okay.
Good enough. So, what do I do next?
I need another matrix, right?
I I need some I I There's There's
another step here.
And I want to express the whole
elimination process in matrix language.
So, tell me what now Now, so next step,
step two
which was what? Subtract
What was What was the actual step that
we did?
I think I subtracted, do you remember?
I had a two in the pivot and a four
below it, so I subtracted
two times
times row two
from row three.
From row
three. Tell me the matrix that'll do
that.
And tell me its name.
Okay, it's going to be
E for elementary or elimination matrix,
and what's the index number that that
that I used to tell me what
E
3 2, right? Because So fixing this
3 2 position. And what's what is the
matrix now?
Okay, you remember so E32 is supposed to
multiply my guy that I have.
And it's supposed to produce
the right result which was it leaves
supposed to leave the first row, it's
supposed to leave the second row, and
it's supposed to straighten out that
third row to
to this.
And what's the matrix that does that?
100, right? Because we don't change the
first row.
And the next row we don't change either.
And the last row is the one we do
change.
And what do I do?
Let's see the
I've subtract two times
So what's this row?
What's this here?
Zero, right? Because the first row is
not involved.
The second it's just in the 32 position,
isn't it?
It's num the key number
is this minus the multiplier that goes
sitting there in that 32 position. So
it's a Is it a minus two?
To subtract two and then this is a one
so that I
I
the the overall effect is to take minus
two of this row plus one of that. Okay.
So I've now given you the pieces.
The elimination matrices, the elementary
matrices that take each step.
So now what?
Now the next
point in the lecture is to put those
steps together
into a matrix that does it all.
And and see how it all happens. So now
I'm going to express the whole,
everything we did today
so far
on on A.
Was to start with A,
we multiplied it by E21.
That was the first step. And then we
multiplied that result by E32.
And that led us to this thing, and what
was that matrix?
U.
You see why I like matrix notation cuz
there in like little space,
a few bits when it's compressed on the
web is everything is this whole lecture.
Okay.
Now,
there are there are important facts
about matrix multiplication.
And we're close to maybe the most
important.
And that that is this. Suppose I ask you
this question. Suppose I start
start with a matrix A,
and I want to end with a matrix U,
and I want to say, what matrix does the
whole job?
What matrix
takes me from A to U?
Using the letters I've got.
So,
and the answer is simple. I'm not asking
this is but it's highly important.
How could I how would I create the
matrix that does the whole job at once?
That does all of elimination in one
shot.
It would be I would just put these
together, right?
In other words, this is the thing I'm
struggling to say.
I can move those parentheses.
If I keep the matrices in order, I can't
mess around with the order of the
matrices, but I can change the order
that I do the multiplications. I can
multiply these two first.
In other words, you see what those
parentheses are doing?
It's saying do multiply the E's first.
And that gives you the matrix that does
everything at once.
Okay.
What So, this fact that this is
automatically the same as this.
For every
matrix multiplication, which I'm
conscious of still not telling you in
every detail.
But like you're seeing how it works.
And this is highly important and maybe
tell me the long word that that
describes this law for matrices. That
that you can move the parentheses.
It's the called the associative law.
I I think you can now forget that.
Uh it's
uh
But don't forget the law. I mean like
forget the word associative. I don't
know. But don't don't forget the law.
Because actually we'll see
so many uh steps in
linear algebra.
So many proofs even of of of main fact
come from just moving the parentheses.
It's a it's like
And it's not that easy to
I mean the to prove to prove that this
is correct, you have to go into the gory
details of matrix multiplication, do it
both ways, and see that you come out the
same.
Maybe I'll leave the uh author to do
that.
Okay. So, there we go.
That's That's
uh
That's how I So, there's a a single
matrix. I I could call it E. Now, oh
while while we're talking about these
matrices,
tell me one other There's another type
of elementary matrix.
And we already said why we might need
it. We We didn't need it in this case,
but it's the matrix that exchanges two
rows.
It's a called a permutation matrix.
Can you just like tell me what that
would be? So, I'm just like this is a
slight digression.
And we'll Yeah, so let me get some Let
me figure out where I'm going to put a
permutation matrix.
You'll see I'm always squeezing stuff
in. So, permutation.
Or in fact, uh this this one uh like
exchange
rows.
So, I exchange rows one and two just to
make life easy.
So, if I had my matrix, uh let me just
do two by two. A B C D.
Suppose I want to find the matrix
that exchanges those rows.
What is it?
So, the matrix that exchanges those
rows, the the row I want is C D and it's
there. So, I I better take one of it.
The row I want here is up top, so I'll
take one of that. So, actually, I've
just the easy way This is the my matrix
that I'll call P
for permutation.
It's the matrix Actually, the the easy
way to find it is just do the thing to
the identity matrix.
Exchange rows Exchange the rows of the
identity matrix, and then
that's the matrix that'll do do row
exchanges for you.
Could Suppose I wanted to exchange
columns instead.
Columns have hardly got into today's
lecture, but they certainly are going to
be around.
How could I if I started with this
matrix ABCD
and then I wouldn't
I
I'm not even going to write this down.
I'm just going to ask you.
Cuz it Cuz in elimination, we're we're
doing rows.
But suppose we wanted to exchange the
columns of a matrix.
How
How would I do that? What What What
matrix multiplication would do that job?
Actually, why not? I'll write it down.
So this is like just
I'll write it under here and then
hide it again.
Okay. Suppose I had my matrix ABCD
and I want to get to
AC over here and BD here.
What matrix does that job?
Can I multiply Can I cook up some matrix
that
produces that answer?
And I You can see from where I put my
hand, I was really asking
can I put a matrix here on the left that
will exchange columns? And the answer is
no.
If I So I'm just bringing out again this
point that when I multiply on the left,
I'm doing row operations. So, if I want
to do a column operation, where do I put
that permutation matrix?
On the
on the right.
If I put it here, where I just barely
left room for it. So, I I'll exchange
the two columns of the identity.
Then it comes out right.
Cuz now I'm multiplying a column at a
time. This This is the first column and
says take one take none of that column,
one of this one, and then you got it.
Over here, take one of this one, none of
this one, and you've got AC.
So,
in short, to do column operations, the
matrix multiplies on the right. To do
row operations, it multiplies on the
left. Okay.
Okay. And it's row operations that we're
really doing.
Okay.
And of course, do it
I I I mentioned in passing, but I better
say it very clearly
that you can't exchange the orders of
matrices. And that's just the point I
was making again here.
A * B is not the same as B * A.
You have to keep these matrices in their
Gauss-given order here, right? You You
But
uh but you can move the parentheses.
So, that In other words, the
commutative law, which would allow you
to
take it in the other order, is false.
So, we have to keep it in that order.
Okay.
So,
uh
What What next?
I could do this multiplication.
I could do E32.
So, let me come back to see what that
was.
Here was
E21.
And here is
E32.
And if I multiply those matrices
together,
E32 and then E21, I'll get a single
matrix that does elimination.
Uh
I don't want to do it that.
I don't I don't
If I do that multiplication,
there there's a better way to do this.
And and and so in this last few minutes
of today's lecture, can I anticipate
that better way?
The better way is to think not how do I
get from A to U,
but how do I get from U back to A?
So,
reversing steps is going to come in.
Inverse
I'll use the word inverse here.
Okay. So, let me make the first step at
what's the inverse matrix.
All the matrices you've seen on this
board have inverses.
I
I didn't write any bad matrices down. We
we spoke about possible failure and for
a moment we put in a matrix that would
fail. But right now, all these matrices
are good. They're all invertible. And
let's take the inverse
Well, let me say first what is the
inverse mean and find it. Okay, so we're
getting a little leg up on inverses.
Okay.
So this is the final
moments of today.
Ah, sorry.
He's still there.
Okay.
Inverses.
Okay, and I'm just going to take one
example and then we're done.
The example I'll take will be that E.
I'm So my matrix is 1 0 0 -3 1 0 0 0 1.
And I want to find the matrix that
undoes
that step.
So what was that step? The step was
subtract three times row one from row
two.
So what matrix will
get me back?
What matrix will bring back
you know, if I started with a 2 12 2 and
it changed it to a 2 6 2 because of this
guy, I want to get back to the 2 12 2.
I want to I want to find the matrix
which which undoes elimination. The
matrix which multiplies this to give the
identity.
And
you can tell me what I should do in
words first and then we'll write down
the matrix that does it.
If this step subtracted three times row
one from row two, what's the inverse
step?
I add
three times row one
to row two, right? I add it back. What I
subtracted away I add back. So, the
inverse matrix in this case is I I now
want to add three times row one to row
two.
So, I won't change row one.
I won't change row three.
And I'll add
three times row one to row two.
That's a case where the inverse is
clear.
It's clear in words what to do.
Because what this did was
simple to express.
It just changed row two by
by subtracting three of row one. So, to
invert it I go that way.
And if you if we do that calculation,
three times this row plus one times this
row comes out the right row of the
identity. Okay. So, inverses are and
So, if this matrix was E
and this matrix is I for identity, then
what's the notation for this guy?
E to the minus one.
E inverse.
Okay.
Let Let's stop there for today. That's
the a little jump on what's coming
on Monday. So, see you Monday.